<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Andreas Taranetz</title><link>https://andreas.taranetz.com/</link><description>Andreas Taranetz' blog about interesting things around software development</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>andreas.taranetz+blog@gmail.com (Andreas Taranetz)</managingEditor><webMaster>andreas.taranetz+blog@gmail.com (Andreas Taranetz)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 20:26:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://andreas.taranetz.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What may we call you?</title><link>https://andreas.taranetz.com/what-may-we-call-you/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 20:26:00 +0200</pubDate><author>Andreas Taranetz</author><guid>https://andreas.taranetz.com/what-may-we-call-you/</guid><description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/hello.png" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>It shouldn&rsquo;t surprise you when I tell you that some websites are collecting too much data about you.
Aside from the obvious privacy issue, this is also a security issue.
You can invest in your security as much as you want and never be 100% safe, but:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You cannot lose what you do not possess.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>First of all, I have to admit that I made this mistake myself in one of my first projects.
I am writing this, so you don&rsquo;t have to make the same mistake.</p>
<h2 id="whats-the-matter">What&rsquo;s the matter?</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve once been working for a startup called <a href="https://kiweno.com/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">kiweno</a> which sells test kits for things like food intolerances.
Like many other websites, they want their users to create an account so all the information from various products can be linked together.
Here is what a part of the registration form looks like:</p>
<p><figure><a class="lightgallery" href="./kiweno-registration-form-large.png" title="./kiweno-registration-form.png" data-thumbnail="./kiweno-registration-form-small.png" data-sub-html="<h2>Registration form asking the user for forename, surname, phone number and gender</h2>">
        
    </a><figcaption class="image-caption">Registration form asking the user for forename, surname, phone number and gender</figcaption>
    </figure>
The form is in German, because this company only targeted the german speaking market.
So in addition to asking for a username and a strong password, the page wanted to know your forename, surname, phone number and gender if you choose to tell them.</p>
<h2 id="whats-wrong-with-that">What&rsquo;s wrong with that?</h2>
<p><a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-5-gdpr/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Article 5 (c) of the GDPR</a> states that</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Personal data shall be: adequate, relevant and limited to what is necessary in relation to the purposes for which they are processed.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is also called the <strong>principle of data minimization</strong>.
In simple terms, this means:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Don&rsquo;t ask for more data than you need [for your product to work]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To reiterate my point from the intro:  The less data you have, the smaller is the risk for your users, should your service get breached.
Let&rsquo;s look into what could be done better with this principle in mind.</p>
<h3 id="communication-channels">Communication channels</h3>
<p>Of course, you almost always need some communication channel to contact your users, but one should be enough to sign up.
In the beginning, the phone number was not mandatory.
To my surprise, the large majority of users still filled in this information since they were asked to.</p>
<p>Having only one input field that ask for <strong>either email or phone</strong> number might be a bit harder to process, but it would make it clear to the user that they do not have to provide both.
The option to fill in the other form of contact could be added on a profile page.</p>
<h3 id="why-even-ask-for-a-gender">Why even ask for a gender?</h3>
<p>In the case of the gender field, the option to not answer is even preselected.
Still, against the default bias, the large majority gave away this information.
Given the medical context, some users might be confused whether this field requires their biological gender, or the gender they identify with.
In both cases there are to few options.</p>
<p>There are some products of kiweno now where your biological gender is required to get a better result.
However, the actual explanation as to why this is already asked at signup is (as so often in software) for legacy reasons.</p>
<p>In the beginning, the assumption was to require this information to correctly address people in e-mails and other form of communication.
Since in German you would use &ldquo;Sehr geehrter Herr&rdquo; / &ldquo;Sehr geehrte Frau&rdquo; in place of &ldquo;Dear&rdquo;.
Later, the marketing team made the great decision to drop this formal tone and use a more informal you (&ldquo;du&rdquo;, which is gender-neutral in German) to address users.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Get rid of your prototypes while you can, or they will haunt you.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="names-are-hard">Names are hard</h3>
<p>Having two separate fields for fore- and surname gives the impression that a user&rsquo;s real name is required.
This might be the case for a bill or shipping address, but - depending on how purchases are processed - this might never need to be persisted in your own system.
I would recommend any startup to let your payment provider deal with this kind of data.</p>
<p>Similar to the gender, the name fields were initially introduced to address users correctly in email conversations.
But again, it is not that simple for all people.
Not every culture uses names the same way.
E.g.: In Spain it is common two have two surnames, one of each parent.
Read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_name" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">wikipedia</a> if you want to go all the way down this rabbit hole.</p>
<p>If the real name of a user is not important to you for legal reasons, I would recommend you to use a single text field asking them <em>&ldquo;What may we call you&rdquo;</em>.
Make sure you reserve enough space in your database so especially my Austrian folks can enter all their acumulated titles.</p>
<h2 id="how-could-we-do-better">How could we do better?</h2>
<p>If there is no immediate use of the data for your product, don&rsquo;t ask for it in advance.</p>
<p>Be aware of how you communicate to your users what kind of data you require from them.</p>
<p>Make it obvious how important or unimportant the accuracy of every field is.
E.g.: don&rsquo;t use a date picker for a birthdate, when the year suffices.</p>
<p>Even if your only target a specific market (e.g.: only German-speaking users), be mindful of users of other cultures that might also are a part of this group.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>whoami</title><link>https://andreas.taranetz.com/whoami/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 13:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>Andreas Taranetz</author><guid>https://andreas.taranetz.com/whoami/</guid><description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/whoami.gif" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><h2 id="let-me-introduce-myself">Let me introduce myself</h2>
<p>As you might have read in the title and the domain name, my name is Andreas and I am working as a software developer.
To share a bit about me, here are a few of my personal preferences:</p>
<ul>
<li>Starter pokémon: <a href="https://pokemon.fandom.com/wiki/Charmander" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Charmander</a></li>
<li>Linux distro: <a href="https://manjaro.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Manjaro</a></li>
<li>Desktop environment: <a href="https://www.gnome.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Gnome</a></li>
<li>Shell: <a href="https://www.zsh.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">ZSH</a> always extended with <a href="https://ohmyz.sh/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">oh-my-zsh</a></li>
<li>Coffee: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caff%C3%A8_Americano" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Americano</a></li>
<li>Color theme: <a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=akamud.vscode-theme-onedark" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Atom One Dark</a></li>
<li>IDE: <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/idea/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Intellij IDEA</a></li>
<li>Command line editor: <a href="https://micro-editor.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">micro</a></li>
<li>The right amount of wheels on a bike: [<a href="https://qu-ax.de/catalog/Muni-Starter-406-mm-20-black" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">1</a>&hellip;<a href="https://www.babboecargobike.com/babboe-curve" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">3</a>]</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="frontend-or-backend-developer">Frontend or backend developer?</h2>
<p>Yes! ☺</p>
<p>In the past, I had the opportunity to work on projects where I was involved in all layers of the stack. From the sizing of the servers up to the spacing of buttons. My ultimate goal would be to become a holistic developer, someone who is knowledgeable about all aspects of software development. Think BizDevSecOps+.</p>
<p>The platform I like to develop for mostly is the browser (of course some more than others).
Although I can justifiably call myself a <a href="https://github.com/holistic-developer/shout-it-out-loud" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Rockstar developer</a> the main languages I work in are Typescript and Java.</p>
<p>I am someone who is easy to get excited about the next cool thing in tech, but I am not blindly jumping on every hype train. We should always try to understand the core problem that needs to be solved, or if there even is a real problem, to begin with.</p>
<p>Sometimes seemingly minor tech decisions can have major implications on the products we build, which is why my favorite interview question is: <em>&ldquo;What do you consider when choosing a new library or dependency&rdquo;</em>.</p>
<p>Independent of the tools or the project I work on, I try to apply Robert C. Martin&rsquo;s variation of the Boy Scout rule:
<strong>&ldquo;Always leave the code cleaner than you found it.&rdquo;</strong></p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>